<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Jordan Thomas</title><link href="http://jthom143.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://jthom143.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://jthom143.github.io/</id><updated>2015-06-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Paper Accepted</title><link href="http://jthom143.github.io/paper-accepted.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jordan Thomas</name></author><id>tag:jthom143.github.io,2015-06-06:paper-accepted.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/2015GL064521/full"&gt;Southern Hemisphere extratropical circulation: Recent trends and natural&amp;nbsp;variability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Southern Ocean has been a region of interest in the last few years due to the detection of possibly significant trends in the Southern Annular Mode (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SAM&lt;/span&gt;) and the mid-latitude westerly jet. Here we quantify the natural variability of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SH&lt;/span&gt; extratropical circulation by using Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 5 (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CMIP5&lt;/span&gt;) preindustrial control model runs and compare with the observed trends in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SAM&lt;/span&gt;, jet magnitude, and jet location. We find that the observed trends in jet location and magnitude are not outside the natural variability as described by these pre-industrial runs, where the observed trend in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SAM&lt;/span&gt; is outside the natural&amp;nbsp;variability. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Figure2" src="images/grl53078-fig-0002.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Natural variability, historical trends, and observations for (a) &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SAM&lt;/span&gt;, (b) 850 mb jet latitude, (c) wind stress jet latitude, (d) 850 mb jet magnitude, and (e) wind stress jet magnitude. Blue circles show the mean of the piControl 25 year linear trends indicating model drift. Whisker length is 2 standard deviations. Red points show the historical run trends for each ensemble member. Horizontal dashed lines indicate the absolute value of the observed trends: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NCEP&lt;/span&gt; R1 (green), &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NCEP&lt;/span&gt; R2 (orange), &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ERA&lt;/span&gt;-Interim (purple), and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JRA&lt;/span&gt;-55&amp;nbsp;(black).&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>